<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Doctrine of the Catholick Church and of the Church of England concerning the blessed Trinity explained and asserted against the dangerous heterodoxes in a sermon by Dr. William Sherlock before my Lord Mayor and the court of aldermen.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12264985</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12264985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 181:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Doctrine of the Catholick Church and of the Church of England concerning the blessed Trinity explained and asserted against the dangerous heterodoxes in a sermon by Dr. William Sherlock before my Lord Mayor and the court of aldermen.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 3-29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Remarks on Dr. Sherlock's sermon of The danger of corrupting the faith by philosophy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Danger of corrupting the faith by philosophy.</term>
               <term>Philosophy and religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57997:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57997:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>REMARKS ON Dr.</hi> SHERLOCK<hi>'s SERMON OF</hi> The Danger of corrupting the Faith by Philoſophy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:57997:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Lately Publiſhed,</head>
            <p>AN Apology for the Parliament, humbly repreſenting to Mr. <hi>John Gailhard</hi> ſome Reaſons why they did not at his Requeſt enact <hi>Sanguinary Laws</hi> againſt Proteſtants in their laſt Seſſion. In two Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by different Hands.</p>
            <p>Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57997:2"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF THE <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> AND OF THE CHURCH of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> CONCERNING THE <hi>Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> Explained, and Aſſerted, Againſt the Dangerous Heterodoxes in a Sermon by Dr. WILLIAM SHERLOCK, before my Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:57997:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57997:3"/>
            <head>Remarks upon Dr. <hi>WILLIAM SHERLOCK</hi>'s (Falſe and Treacherous) Defence, and Explication, of ſome principal Articles of Faith; in a Sermon, before my Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen, on <hi>April 25. 1697.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I No ſooner ſaw the Title of this Sermon, <hi>The Danger of corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Faith, by Philoſophy;</hi> and the Text, <hi>Let no man ſpoil you, through Philoſophy;</hi> but I imagined what was the Author's deſign. To protect himſelf from, and to be revenged upon, the <hi>Oxford-Heads,</hi> and the famous <hi>Decree</hi> there made; by an Inſult upon <hi>the Learning of the Place,</hi> upon <hi>Philoſophy</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>He addreſſes his Sermon againſt <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Againſt Philoſophy, on the Authority of a (miſtaken) Text of Scripture. Againſt Reaſon, on his own Authority, but not without a juſt provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation we may be ſure; <hi>becauſe he found Reaſon was firſt againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſon, Sagacity, Knowledg, Wiſdom, are but only ſeveral names of the ſame thing; and I never heard of any thing that Reaſon was againſt, or that was againſt Reaſon, but only <hi>Folly</hi> or <hi>Falſhood.</hi> Therefore, tho there have been ſome, as particularly great <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> who <hi>jeſtingly</hi> wrote <hi>Encomium moriae,</hi> the Praiſe of Folly: I did not expect that a Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s would have <hi>preach'd</hi> for Folly, becauſe I took preaching to be a <hi>ſerious</hi> Exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> had a mind to declaim againſt Reaſon, and againſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy: Why? For the ſake, he ſaith, of certain <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> that are in great and preſent danger, from Philoſophy and Reaſon, What, Man; wilt thou ſay then that there are Articles of Faith which diſagree with Reaſon, and with Philoſophy? Reaſon being nothing elſe but <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> nor Philoſophy, but the Obſervations and Experiments that have been made concerning the nature of things, in one word
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57997:4"/>
               <hi>Experience:</hi> This Undertaking, to defend the Articles of Faith, by decrying Reaſon and Philoſophy, is to ſay in effect, the Articles of Faith are not conſiſtent either with <hi>natural Wiſdom,</hi> or with <hi>experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Knowledg.</hi> Than which a more dangerous, or more opprobrious thing could not be ſaid, by <hi>Vaninus,</hi> or <hi>Hobbs,</hi> or other the rankeſt Atheiſt in the World: In very deed, 'tis <hi>the whole</hi> that Atheiſts and Infidels would perſwade; they reckon, and ſo far forth they reckon truly, that they gain their point by ſuch a Conceſſion.</p>
            <p>This kind of Defence therefore, is as falſe and treacherous, as our Author's Explication, of the Articles intended, is heretical and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian. <hi>Non tali auxilio, non defenſoribus iſtis;</hi> the Articles of Faith lack no ſuch Defences, or Defenders. Tho all of them are not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable by meer Philoſophy, or by natural unaſſiſted Reaſon, yet they perfectly agree with both; and receive light and confirmation from 'em.</p>
            <p>Well; but ſeeing the Doctor had taken a conceit againſt Philoſophy; Why did he chooſe this Text, ſo contrary, in the opinion of all <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters,</hi> to his purpoſe? For they are all of opinion, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks not of Philoſophy in general, but of <hi>the Platonick</hi> Philoſophy; and more eſpecially of the notions of that Philoſophy, concerning <hi>a Trinity of Divine Spirits</hi> and <hi>Subſtances:</hi> which Notions are the very ſame with Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s, as is not only confeſſed, but moſt largely proved, by the chief Aſſertor of them, Dr. <hi>Cudworth.</hi> See Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synop. Critic. in loc.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi>'s <hi>Intel. Syſtem,</hi> p. 546, <hi>&amp; deinceps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us make an Abſtract or Summary of this Sermon: of the Points or Doctrines, it advances; and of the Reaſonings, that are uſed here, to ſupport them. And afterwards, conſider briefly, both the one and the other. He obſerves,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That,</hi> Philoſophy and Reaſon are the only things, which thoſe men adore, who would have no God at all. And <hi>that,</hi> what makes ſome men Atheiſts and Infidels; even the Philoſophick Tincture, and their adherence to Natural Reaſon: the ſame makes others to be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; that is, to be Arians, Socinians, and Pelagians. <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. and 6. and 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That,</hi> to find the true Chriſtian Faith, we muſt attend only to Scripture. Not to the meer <hi>Words,</hi> or <hi>Phraſes,</hi> there uſed; for ſuch a Confeſſion or Declaration of the Faith would leave all the Hereſies untouch'd, and all Hereticks in quiet poſſeſſion of their Opinions;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57997:4"/>becauſe they all ſubmit to the <hi>Words,</hi> and <hi>Phraſes</hi> of Scripture. But for aſcertaining what is the true Faith, we muſt attend to Scripture only, in this Senſe; namely, to what is the <hi>true Meaning</hi> of Scripture-words and Phraſes: to <hi>that</hi> Meaning which <hi>the Phraſe</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> do imply; rejecting all mixture of Philoſophy and natural Reaſon, in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes and <hi>Inquiries, concerning the Meaning of Scripture.</hi> P. 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That,</hi> as we are Chriſtians; and unleſs we will be underſtood, to reject the ſupreme Authority of Revelation, we muſt believe thoſe Doctrines that are moſt myſterious and unconceivable: notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>any</hi> Objections from Natural Reaſon, and from Philoſophy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 'em. Whereupon he hath this Aphoriſm; He that believes no farther than natural Reaſon approves, believes his Reaſon, and not the Revelation; he is a natural Philoſopher, not a Believer. <hi>P.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That,</hi> Difficulty of conceiving a thing, nay the <hi>abſolute <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs</hi> of it, muſt not hinder our Aſſent to what is contained in <hi>Divine Revelation:</hi> becauſe we do not disbelieve what is made known to us, by <hi>Senſe,</hi> or by <hi>Reaſon;</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>any Difficulty,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivableneſs,</hi> adhering to it. And as to <hi>Contradictions,</hi> ſo often ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in theſe caſes: 'tis an eaſy matter, to find Contradictions in what we do not underſtand; when we will be reaſoning on what we do not underſtand, there will be <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Impoſſibilities</hi> innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, in our Gueſſes about 'em. <hi>P.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>After this, he anſwers to two Objections; whereof the firſt is, That it ſeems very unnatural, that God having made us Reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and thereby having made natural Reaſon the meaſure of Truth and Falſhood to us, we ſhould notwithſtanding be required to believe without Reaſon. If we muſt believe with our Underſtandings; how can we believe what we do not underſtand? To this he anſwers, by ſaying; when an Objection is made againſt any thing, or that it is (as we apprehend) <hi>without</hi> Reaſon, or againſt and <hi>contrary</hi> to Reaſon: the Objection is of no value, if ſuch thing is not the proper Object of Reaſon; ſuch as the Natures and Eſſences of things, their eſſential Reaſons, their Unions, Operations, and Properties: which no Man (he ſaith) can pretend, are the Objects of Reaſon, or that any Man living can know any thing of them. And this, he adds, is all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibility and Contradiction that Men can charge on the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of the Trinity and Incarnation. <hi>P.</hi> 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Objection is; To what purpoſe can ſuch a Revelation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57997:5"/>ſerve, or of what uſe can ſuch a Faith be, which is concerning things we cannot comprehend or underſtand; and to which Reaſon diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees? He anſwers, <hi>Firſt;</hi> we may uſe the <hi>World,</hi> and every thing in it, as fully and to as good purpoſe; as if we underſtood the Reaſons, and internal Natures of things. The Objection, if it hath any force, takes place, as much againſt created Nature, or the Complex of things called the <hi>World,</hi> as againſt the Goſpel-Myſteries of the Trinity and Incarnation: for the former is all <hi>inconceivable Myſtery,</hi> as well as the latter. He anſwers again, <hi>Secondly;</hi> Tho we underſtand not the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> or the neceſſity of the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> by the Death of the Son of God: 'tis for all that a very <hi>uſeful</hi> Knowledg, even this, that <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son; to the end, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi> P. 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>This is the Subſtance, and Force of the Sermon. And one would think, on a general View of this Diſcourſe; that all Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Care and Concern were for the poor diſtreſſed Articles of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith: that there is nothing in his Thoughts, however nothing equally in his Thoughts; as the <hi>Defence</hi> and Patronage of the (Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrines of the) Trinity, the Incarnation, and Satisfaction. But I know no body but himſelf, and his Party of <hi>Realiſts,</hi> as they call themſelves, that queſtion the Articles of the Trinity, the Incarnation, or the Satisfaction, in the Senſe they are held by the Catholick Church. It is even neceſſary to caution his Hearers, and Readers, what this Doctor's true meaning is, when he pretends to plead for the Trinity, and the Articles thereon depending. For when he cries <hi>Trinity,</hi> he means <hi>three Eternal and Infinite Spirits;</hi> that is, he ſays Trinity, and means <hi>Tritheiſm:</hi> and this is the Reaſon, why his Defences of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Doctrine of the Trinity, are as falſe and weak, as his Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Doctrine, that I may uſe the words of the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Decree concerning it, is <hi>heretical and impious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Catholick Church believes; <hi>that</hi> Almighty God is <hi>one</hi> Infinite and Eternal Spirit. <hi>That</hi> the Divinity was ſo incarnate in the Humanity of the Lord Chriſt, as to exert in it the Divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes: as <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> or the Knowledg of the Thoughts, and of the Future; and <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> or the Power of Miracles. Whereupon there followed (as Divines ſpeak) <hi>a Communication of Idioms:</hi> Which is to ſay, in conſideration of this Incarnation, we ſay <hi>God was made
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57997:5"/>Man;</hi> and <hi>the Lord Chriſt is true God.</hi> But by the former, 'tis only meant, that by his Incarnation or Indwelling in the Humanity, it may be ſaid, (ſomewhat Catachreſtically or improperly) that <hi>God became Man:</hi> by the other, <hi>that the Lord Chriſt is true God,</hi> is meant; he is <hi>God</hi> (and whatſoever may be ſaid of God) <hi>in reſpect of God in him.</hi> Farther, <hi>that</hi> our Bleſſed Saviour by his <hi>active</hi> and <hi>paſſive</hi> Obedience, <hi>did reconcile</hi> Men to God, and God to Men, and <hi>ſatisfied</hi> whatſoever the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God required for the Pardon of Sin, and the Donation of eternal Life; on the Conditions however (on our part) of Faith, Repentance, and Newneſs of Life.</p>
            <p>As to the Divine Perſons, <hi>that</hi> the Divine Eſſence or Subſtance, or the Divinity it ſelf, can be no otherwiſe diſtinguiſhed or diverſified, but only (as the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> words this matter) by <hi>different Modes of Subſiſtence,</hi> or <hi>relative Properties:</hi> which, being conſidered together with the Divine Eſſence and Attributes, are named <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Faith all the Denominations of Chriſtians do acquieſce. As it is the <hi>Churches</hi> Doctrine, and <hi>her whole Doctrine</hi> about theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; 'tis alſo imbraced, by all <hi>the Sects</hi> of Chriſtians, except only the Arians: of which Perſwaſion there are none (I think) in <hi>England;</hi> nor in the Dominions of any Chriſtian Prince or State. But Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> and with him ſome few others, endeavour to diſturb this happy Agreement and Conſent; they would divide us by novel Doctrines, and a new Explication of the Trinity: an Explication which is as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Polytheiſm and Paganiſm, as any of the (old or modern) Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were ever guilty of. He hath not indeed in this <hi>Sermon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared expreſly, what kind of Trinity he pleads for; but he intimates it, and plainly points to it, at <hi>p.</hi> 7, and 10. He owns (at <hi>p.</hi> 10.) 'tis the <hi>new Explication;</hi> and at <hi>p.</hi> 7. the <hi>real Trinity:</hi> by which Names (all Men know) he and his Party call their <hi>Trinity of Spirits and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> in all their Books. Therefore, tho if another Man had preached this Sermon; the Errors and Weakneſſes, for which 'tis ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, might have been charitably overlook'd: yet coming from him who deſigns to eſtabliſh a Hereſy, that ſubverts the grand Deſign of Chriſtianity, and revives Paganiſm, under the diſguiſe of a (falſe) Zeal for the Catholick Doctrines of the Trinity, the Incarnation, and the Satisfaction; it would be a very drowſy Neglect, not to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and warning of this <hi>Wolf in Sheeps Clothing;</hi> or not to detect the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57997:6"/>
               <hi>Falſeneſs</hi> of his Reaſonings, as well as <hi>the Impiety</hi> of his Principles and Doctrine. I come therefore now to a particular Diſcuſſion of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parts of his Sermon, which I have already repreſented in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> was: <q rend="inline">Philoſophy and Reaſon are the only things which thoſe Men adore, who would have no God at all. And what makes ſome Men <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Infidels;</hi> even the Philoſophick Tincture, and their Adherence to natural-Reaſon: the ſame makes others to be <hi>Hereticks;</hi> that is, to be Arians, Socinians, and Pelagians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He intended it, without doubt, as a mighty Prejudice againſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Philoſophy, that Atheiſts and Infidels pretend to both; and that they ſeem to eſteem nothing elſe. And, in truth, a notable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning it is, for a Sermon; as Sermons ordinarily now go: but from the Preſs, or in a Book, 'tis a contemptible Weakneſs. Atheiſts, and Infidels, magnify Philoſophy, and Reaſon: therefore Divines, and good Chriſtians, muſt be hence cautioned, that Philoſophy and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will deſpoil 'em of <hi>their Piety</hi> towards God, and their <hi>Faith</hi> as Chriſtians. Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam,</hi> is often quoted, for a contrary Aphoriſm, namely this: that indeed <q rend="inline">a ſmattering in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, inclines Men to Atheiſm and Irreligion; but a Maſtery in it, <hi>begets</hi> and <hi>nouriſhes</hi> Piety and Faith.</q> And ſurely, Experience has ſhown, he was in the right. For thoſe Divines, who have alſo been <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> are the Men, that have by their Writings done the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt ſucceſsful Service to Religion. Which, in ſuch an Age as this, would hardly have ſtood its Ground, under the Management of Divines, that were not Philoſophers alſo.</p>
            <p>The Weapons of Atheiſts and infidels, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſaith, are Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Reaſon: I am of opinion, they muſt be beaten at their own Weapons; or they will never be beaten. Yield but to them Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Reaſon; the Advantage, I fear, will be judged to be on their ſide. I wonder how this Doctor, who is for excluding Reaſon and Philoſophy, as Enemies to Divine Truth, would deal with the Atheiſts and Infidels. But it may be, he would buy him a maſſy Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-Bible, with Claſps and Boſſes, and knock 'em down with it.</p>
            <p>And it troubles him ſadly too, that Philoſophy and Reaſon are the Weapons of <hi>Hereticks;</hi> of Arians, and Socinians, and Pelagians: as well as of Atheiſts and Infidels. And from hence he infers, as before; that it was this ſame (ſcurvy) Philoſophy, and Reaſon, that <hi>made 'em
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57997:6"/>Hereticks.</hi> Without doubt this was intended at the <hi>Oxford Heads.</hi> Thoſe moroſe old Gentlemen that could not let a Man alone, in a ſmall ſlip, but muſt be decreeing, and cenſuring, as ſoon as ever 'tis ſaid or printed that there are <hi>three</hi> Eternal and Infinite Spirits: 'tis but fit they ſhould be told their own; that 'tis they, with their <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> and their Logicks, or <hi>Art of Reaſoning,</hi> that make all the Hereticks. And yet 'tis thought, by ſome odd Fellows, on the other hand; that Philoſophy and Reaſon never cauſed that Miſcheif that our Preacher pretends: and they offer, to confirm what they ſay, by the Example of the Arch Heretick <hi>Socinus:</hi> Who never underſtood <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> nor ſo much as Logicks, or the Art of <hi>Reaſoning,</hi> till the latter part of his Life. Toward the latter part of his Life, he got ſome Skill in the <hi>Sophiſmatical part</hi> of Logick, and wrote a little Treatiſe about it. Howe're it be; I find, 'tis like to go hard with Philoſophy; whatever becomes of Reaſon. For Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> warns, in effect, my Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, that they take care, that their Children may never ſee <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridg;</hi> for there they will catch <hi>the Infection of Rhiloſophy;</hi> and after that, 'tis certain they will be Hereticks, Arians, or Socinians, or Pelagians. The Hereticks on the other ſide, many of them, are no leſs bitter againſt this ſame (dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable) Philoſophy: they proteſt, eſpecially in their Latin Works; that 'tis Philoſophy that corrupted and debauch'd Divinity. I wiſh in my heart theſe Gentlemen (the Doctor and the Hereticks) do not play booty, into one anothers hands: for as angry as they would ſeem againſt one another, 'tis plain, they join Stocks againſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</p>
            <p>As for poor Reaſon, and the Hurt ſhe does, in ſeducing Men from the true Faith; I will conſider what may be ſaid in the caſe, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part (a more opportune place) of this Anſwer; and content my ſelf to make here this one Reflection. 'Tis very ſurprizing to me, that this Doctor ſhould turn <hi>Heretick-taker;</hi> when he himſelf ſtands cenſured of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and in the very point of the Trinity, by Decree of the moſt famous Univerſity in the World. Not only ſo, but ſome Learned and Orthodox Writers, as great <hi>Anti-pelagians</hi> as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, pretend to a Diſcovery, that <hi>he</hi> and his Party of <hi>Realiſts</hi> are <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians;</hi> and ſtart juſt from the ſame place, from whence <hi>L. Socinus, Ochinus, Blandrata,</hi> and other Founders of Socinianiſm, firſt ſet forth. They prove this Charge, by two things: Firſt, that the Doctrine of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57997:7"/>Dean <hi>Sherlock</hi> concerning the Divine Perſons, is exactly the ſame, with the Hereſy of <hi>Laelius Socinus, B. Ochinus, G. Blandrata, V. Gentilis,</hi> and other Founders of Socinianiſm: they all teach alike, three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Eſſences, Subſtances,</hi> and <hi>Spirits.</hi> And whereas, againſt this ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one would be ready to object; that three infinite Spirituall <hi>Eſſences,</hi> three Eternal all-perfect <hi>Spirits,</hi> muſt needs be three Gods: againſt which the Scripture is poſitive; aſſerting every where, that there is <hi>but one God.</hi> They anſwer'd, there is <hi>but one God;</hi> the Father is that <hi>one God,</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> the <hi>moſt High God,</hi> and <hi>God of the other two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons.</hi> The reaſon is, <hi>the Father only is unoriginated;</hi> the Son and Spirit are originated from the Father, as their <hi>Fountain and Cauſe:</hi> this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Pre-eminence of the Father, doth intitle him to the name of <hi>the God</hi> by way of Excellence, <hi>the one God,</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> the <hi>moſt High God;</hi> nay and of <hi>God of the Son,</hi> according to that of our Saviour himſelf, <hi>I aſcent—to my God and to your God.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> diſſolveth the objected Difficulty after the ſame manner. For when he hath ſaid, three Infinite <hi>Eſſences,</hi> three Eternal <hi>Spirits;</hi> he ſaith alſo <hi>but one God:</hi> and interprets thoſe words, <hi>I aſcend to my Father and your Father, to my God and your God,</hi> as <hi>L. Socinus</hi> (and that <hi>Junto</hi>) did; namely thus, in theſe very words. <q rend="inline">There is no Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in owning, that the Father is <hi>the Head,</hi> and the <hi>God,</hi> of the Son, as the Son is a Divine Perſon: for the Father is <hi>the Fountain of the Deity.</hi> The Son being only <hi>God of God,</hi> [that is, God origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from God, namely from God the Father] therefore the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be called <hi>his God.</hi>
               </q> Vindic. of the Trin. <hi>p.</hi> 154. The <hi>other</hi> Proof of the Charge of Socinianiſm againſt the Dean; and of a deſign to introduce it, is; that the Doctrine of three <hi>Eſſences</hi> and three <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> doth lead, <hi>by neceſſary and unavoidable Conſequences,</hi> to the Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm that is <hi>now</hi> ſo called. For tho <hi>Laelius Socinus, Blandrata,</hi> and the reſt, did abide a while in it; that three <hi>Eſſences,</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> are one God, becauſe only the firſt of them is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unoriginated as to his Being and Godhead, the other two derive Being and Godhead from him: yet after ſome time, it was perceived by 'em, that three Infinite <hi>Eſſences,</hi> three all-perfect <hi>Spirits,</hi> are not the leſs three Gods, becauſe the ſecond and third are originated from the firſt; for it can be only ſaid in the caſe, that the firſt God generated two other Gods. Originated or not originated is not what maketh a God, but <hi>Omnimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Perfection;</hi> therefore if the ſecond and third Spirits are each of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57997:7"/>them All-perfect, he is not lefs a God, than the firſt is. This Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gave birth, to the modern Socinianiſm, or the Socinianiſm that <hi>now</hi> is; for <hi>Laelius Socinus</hi> ſoon dying, his Nephew <hi>Fauſtus Socinus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced <hi>Blandrata,</hi> and the others, that they muſt no longer ſay three <hi>Eſſences</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> but <hi>one</hi> Eſſence, <hi>one</hi> Spirit; and alſo, but <hi>one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ Fauſtus Socinus</hi> took <hi>Perſon,</hi> and intellectual Eſſence or <hi>intellectual Subſtance,</hi> to ſignify the ſame thing; he thought them, equivalent terms: therefore, becauſe he plainly ſaw, that three (Infinite All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect) <hi>Eſſences</hi> or <hi>Spirits</hi> are certainly three <hi>Gods;</hi> he contended, being neither a Critick nor a Metaphyſician, that as there is <hi>but one Divine Eſſence or Spirit,</hi> we ought alſo to ſay there is <hi>but one Divine Perſon.</hi> In ſhort; the Dean's more warm Oppoſers ſay, his Doctrine (of a Trinity of <hi>Eſſences</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi>) is the ſame that was affirmed by <hi>Laelinus Socinus,</hi> and other Founders of Socinianiſm: and that in its Conſquences, it leads to the modern (or preſent) Socinianiſm, the Socinianiſm of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus;</hi> for the Unity of God, or that there is <hi>but one God,</hi> can never be defended, by <hi>theſe</hi> Men who hold <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>intellectual Subſtance</hi> to be the ſame, but only on the Principles of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> and the <hi>modern</hi> Socinians. Thus, I ſay, ſome Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Writers argue; they are perſwaded, that as this Doctor main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Hereſy of <hi>Laelius Socinus;</hi> he muſt, of neceſſity, by attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>the Conſequences</hi> of his Doctrine, make a Coalition or Cloſure (in the end) with <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> and the <hi>preſent</hi> Socinianiſm; if it be not already his Opinion, and Aim. As for Subſcriptions, Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſuch like; Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> may multiply them, as much as he pleaſes: but they are reſolved, never to believe him; for they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that his Predeceſſors (L. <hi>Socinus, G. Blandrata,</hi> &amp;c.) never ſtuck at ſuch Matters; but made uſe of 'em <hi>as Artifices,</hi> to get into Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Eſteem with the Orthodox, and then ſeduce them. But, for my part, I judg the Dean, tho moſt certainly a Diſciple of <hi>Laeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Socinus,</hi> may eaſily be brought off, from the Imputation of being a Socinian, according to the Model of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> and the <hi>preſent</hi> Socinians. For, it is true, he holds three <hi>Eſſences</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> and he thinks, <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>intellectual Subſtance</hi> ſignify the ſame thing, ſo that in multiplying the one you neceſſarily multiply the other: and it is no leſs true, that on theſe two Principles, or <hi>in conſequence</hi> of theſe two Principles; he can never defend the Unity of God, but on the grounds of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> and the modern Socinians; namely, that God is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57997:8"/>indeed <hi>but one Perſon.</hi> I ſay, I grant, both theſe Imputations on the Doctor, are true: and yet it will not follow, that in very deed he is a Socinian after the Model of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> or aims to introduce the Socinian Scheme, as 'tis held by the Modern Socinians. For having diſclaimed the uſe of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in Matters of Religion, he is bound up by no <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences,</hi> tho never ſo clear or certain: for all <hi>Conſequences</hi> are the Children of Reaſon; againſt which (in Diſputes of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Articles of Faith</hi>) the Doctor has proteſted, before my Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen. If it be never ſo certain, that he holds as <hi>Laelius Socinus</hi> did; and never ſo evident, that <hi>the neceſſary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> from thence, is the Scheme of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus:</hi> this can never affect him; who diſclaiming <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is therefore diſcharged of the fooliſh Trouble, of <hi>attending to Conſequences;</hi> which are mere <hi>Brats of Reaſon.</hi> He may be as clear of any Deſign to introduce the Scheme of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus;</hi> notwithſtanding theſe Suſpicions, of ſome right Orthodox Men; as he is, of bringing in <hi>Presbytery;</hi> which, in my heart, I cannot think he intends, now he is become a <hi>Dean.</hi> We have ſaid enough, to his firſt Propoſition; that Reaſon, and Philoſophy, are the two Idols of Atheiſts and Hereticks: and that make Atheiſts to be Atheiſts, and Hereticks to be Hereticks.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Second.</head>
               <p>He ſaith again: <q rend="inline">That to aſcertain what is the very and true Faith, we muſt attend only to <hi>that</hi> Meaning of Scripture which <hi>the Words</hi> and <hi>Phraſes</hi> do imply: rejecting all mixture of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> in our Diſputes about Religion, and our <hi>Inquiries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Meaning</hi> of Scripture.</q> That is, he is for giving up the Proteſtant Religion; to the Old Gentleman at <hi>Rome;</hi> and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion in general, to the certain Triumph of Deiſts and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. Reaſon and Philoſophy, he ſaith, muſt not be admitted into our Diſputes about Religion, or our Inquiries concerning the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture: no, the <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Phraſes</hi> of Scripture, in their obvious and natural Senſe, are the only things, that muſt determine our Diſputes, form the Articles of Religion, and ſettle the meaning of Scripture. For inſtance, the Queſtion is, concerning the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation: the <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Phraſes</hi> are theſe; <hi>This is my Body. My FLESH is Meat indeed, my BLOOD is Drink indeed. He that eateth my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57997:8"/>FLESH, and drinketh my BLOOD, the ſame dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi> Yes, ſay <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> the Lord Chriſt had <hi>a Body,</hi> and that Body was <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi> but when Bread is called his <hi>Body</hi> or his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and Wine his <hi>Blood;</hi> it could not be intended that Bread is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Fleſh, or Wine is Blood, <hi>in reality of the thing,</hi> but only <hi>in ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication or ſign.</hi> Bread is the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt, and Wine his <hi>Blood,</hi> by way of ſign and ſignification: and to ſay otherwiſe is <hi>a Contradiction</hi> to the nature of the things ſpoken of, that is, to <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> which aſſures us that the real Body of Chriſt cannot be in Heaven, and on the Altar, at the ſame time. Exclude, now, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Philoſophy out of this Diſpute, and from the Enquiry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>the meaning</hi> of the words and phraſes of Scripture, about this matter, and it will be undeniable that the advantage is wholly on the Popiſh ſide: a Proteſtant Doctor, and he too a Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> gives away our only Strengths againſt the common Adverſary. Our Saviour ſays of a piece of Bread, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> if now Reaſon and Philoſophy muſt not interpret, How will Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> avoid, either the Papiſt on the one ſide, or the Lutheran on the other? He cannot have recourſe to <hi>Senſe,</hi> in the caſe; 'tis only Philoſophy or Reaſon that muſt help him out: for tho the Apoſtles who <hi>ſaw</hi> and <hi>taſted</hi> that it was Bread only, and not Fleſh, might have appealed alſo to their <hi>Senſes;</hi> yet <hi>we</hi> that never ſaw or taſted the Subſtance which Jeſus gave then to the Diſciples, can know by <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy</hi> only, by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, that it was not his Fleſh and Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We argue,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">He took <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed it,</hi> and gave to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and ſaid, <hi>Take, eat, This is my Body.</hi>
                  </q> The Text expreſly ſays it was <hi>Bread</hi> which he bleſſed and brake, and called it <hi>his Body; therefore,</hi> it was his Body <hi>in ſign and ſignification,</hi> not in <hi>reality.</hi> All this is <hi>arguing;</hi> 'tis <hi>Reaſon</hi> that convinces <hi>us,</hi> not <hi>Senſe,</hi> that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance he divided to them was indeed Bread, not <hi>his Fleſh,</hi> which he neither bleſſed nor brake.</p>
               <p>But if our Preacher ſays, he believes it was only Bread, <hi>becauſe the Text it ſelf calls it Bread;</hi> let him conſider, that ſeeing what was called <hi>Bread,</hi> before Chriſt <hi>bleſſed it;</hi> after the Bleſſing he calls it <hi>his Body:</hi> We cannot know, by <hi>Senſe</hi> or by <hi>the Text,</hi> but by Reaſon and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy only, that it was not changed (by the Bleſſing) into what now he calls it, namely <hi>his Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57997:9"/>
               <p>The Papiſts believe it was <hi>Bread</hi> that Chriſt <hi>took:</hi> but becauſe when he had <hi>brake</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> it, he calls it <hi>his Body;</hi> they conclude, that <hi>by the Bleſſing</hi> it was changed into <hi>the ſubſtance</hi> of Fleſh, but without change of <hi>the Accidents.</hi> I ſay now, tho <hi>Senſe</hi> might interpret the words <hi>this is my Body</hi> to the Apoſtles, who <hi>ſaw</hi> it and <hi>taſted</hi> it, yet to <hi>us</hi> (who neither ſaw nor taſted) thoſe words cannot be rightly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, but only by <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> becauſe, tho <hi>the Text</hi> alſo calls it <hi>Bread,</hi> yet not after it was bleſſed.</p>
               <p>I might give a hundred the like Inſtances, but I think 'tis not worth while; for there is no man of any conſideration but will acknowledg, from the force of this one Example, that Philoſophy and Reaſon may be very uſeful in the Diſputes about Religion, and for aſcertaining <hi>the meaning</hi> of Scripture; and that by no means ſhould they be wholly excluded, as this Noveller pretends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Third.</head>
               <q> As we are Chriſtians, and unleſs we will be underſtood to reject the Supream Authority of Divine Revelation, we muſt believe thoſe Doctrines which are thought to be <hi>moſt</hi> myſterious and inconceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, notwithſtanding <hi>any</hi> Objections from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or from <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> againſt 'em. He that believes no farther than Natural Reaſon approves, believes his Reaſon, and not the Revelation; he is a <hi>Natural Philoſopher,</hi> not <hi>a Believer.</hi> He believes the Scriptures, as he would believe <hi>Plato</hi> or <hi>Tully;</hi> not as they are inſpired Writings, but as agreeable to Reaſon, and as the Reſult of wiſe and deep Thoughts.</q>
               <p>I ſhufft my Candle, and put on my Spectacles, when I read this; I could not believe but that I miſtook, for want of a better ſight: but Spectacles and Candle both ſtood to it, that my Eyes had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me. I entreat therefore <hi>the Dean of St. Pauls,</hi> to reconcile what he ſays here, with as clear a Paſſage, in <hi>Dr. Sherlock</hi>'s <hi>Vindication of the Trinity, pag.</hi> 151. where the Doctor ſays: <q rend="inline">Suppoſe, that the <hi>natural Conſtruction</hi> of the words of Scripture import ſuch a Senſe, as is contrary to ſome evident Principle of <hi>Reaſon? Then I won't believe it.</hi> How, not believe Scripture? No, no; I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no pretended <hi>Revelation,</hi> which contradicts the plain Dictates of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Were I perſwaded that the Books called <hi>Holy Scripture</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57997:9"/> did contradict the plain Dictates of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I would not believe 'em.</q> If this <hi>Vindication of the Trinity</hi> was written, as the Doctor intimates in the Preface to it, by <hi>Divine Inſpiration;</hi> it would tempt one to think that his Sermon, before my Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen, was compoſed by <hi>Diabolical Suggeſtion;</hi> for no man, not the Doctor himſelf, will deny, that they directly contradict one another. The <hi>Sermon</hi> ſays, we are to believe the <hi>moſt</hi> myſterious and inconceivable Doctrines, notwithſtanding <hi>any</hi> Objections of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> the inſpired <hi>Vindication</hi> ſays, we are not to believe Scripture if it contradicts <hi>Reaſon.</hi> The <hi>Sermon</hi> ſays, to believe no farther than <hi>Reaſon</hi> approves, is to be a Philoſopher, not a Believer: the <hi>Vindication</hi> (divinely ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted) ſays, if <hi>Reaſon</hi> approves not, but gainſays or contradicts, we are not to believe whatſoever <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to that, which he intended (I imagine) as a choice Thought; that to believe no farther than <hi>Reaſon</hi> approves, is to believe the Scriptures but only as we would believe <hi>Plato</hi> or <hi>Tully.</hi> It will not help the <hi>Preacher</hi> in the leaſt. For when the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> or any other man, ſees cauſe, to disbelieve ſomewhat in <hi>Tully</hi> or <hi>Plato;</hi> he conſiders that, tho they were indeed great men, yet being but men, they were fallible; it might readily happen that they overſaw in ſome particular matter, overſaw what leſs able Perſons might happen to diſcern. But when Reaſon cannot approve Doctrines, ſaid by ſome to be contained <hi>in Scripture;</hi> as ſuppoſe, <hi>three</hi> Infinite <hi>Spirits,</hi> each of them a God, and yet all of them but <hi>one</hi> God: an honeſt man will eaſily find a great many Expedients, much better than <hi>the Vindicator</hi>'s downright <hi>I won't believe the Scriptures;</hi> He will ſay, for example: Let us examine very carefully, whether this contradictory impoſſible (and heretical) Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; three Infinite <hi>Spirits,</hi> each of them a perfect God, all of them but one; is indeed affirmed any where in Scripture? It is not found there, beſure, in expreſs words; it only ſeems to ſome few Upſtarts, <hi>to be implied</hi> in ſome Paſſages of Scripture: therefore, ſays the honeſt Chriſtian, if thoſe Paſſages bid any thing fair, toward ſuch a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; it's better however to ſuppoſe, 'tis more congruous to think, that an Inſpired Writer uſes a <hi>figurative,</hi> or it may be a <hi>catachreſtical</hi> Expreſſion or Phraſe, than that he delivers flat Contradictions, or downright Impoſſibilities.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, I ſay; there is an honeſt Medium, between Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Impious <hi>I won't believe the Scriptures,</hi> and between believing what <hi>Reaſon</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57997:10"/>and <hi>Philoſophy</hi> do abſolutely reject. It is this, That we know the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Writers do often ſpeak figuratively, nay often catachreſtically or improperly: All Interpreters confeſs ſo much. There is hardly a Chapter in the Bible where they do not obſerve it more than once; and therefore mollify the <hi>words</hi> or <hi>phraſe</hi> by a dexterous Interpretation. So that neither <hi>the Vindicator,</hi> after all his pretences to Inſpiration, is to be heard, when he cries, <hi>I won't believe the Scripture:</hi> nor yet the <hi>Preacher,</hi> when he cants to my Lord Mayor and the Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, That no Objections of <hi>Reaſon</hi> can be admitted againſt the meer <hi>Phraſes</hi> and <hi>words</hi> of Scripture. A Rule of Interpreting, that would let in the Tranſubſtantiation, and a hundred more abſurd and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On the Fourth.</head>
               <p>He tells us next. <q rend="inline">Difficulty of conceiving a thing, nay the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute unconceivableneſs of it, muſt not hinder our aſſent to what is contained in <hi>Revelation; becauſe</hi> we do not disbelieve what is made known to us by <hi>Senſe,</hi> or by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> notwithſtanding any <hi>Difficulty</hi> or <hi>Inconceivableneſs</hi> adhering to ſuch things. And as to <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> ſo often objected in theſe caſes; 'tis an eaſy matter to find Contradictions in what we do not underſtand: when we will be reaſoning on what we do not underſtand, there will be <hi>Contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Impoſſibilities</hi> innumerable, in our Gueſſes about 'em.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſincerely believe that God may reveal to us many things, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable or unconceivable, not only by the Humane Underſtanding, but by the Angelical. But 'tis not true, what our Preacher here adds, by way of confirmation or proof; namely, that we believe what is made known to us by <hi>Senſe,</hi> or by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>any</hi> difficulty or inconceivableneſs, adhering to ſome ſuch things. For <hi>Senſe</hi> tells me, that <hi>the Oar</hi> in the Water <hi>is crooked;</hi> that all diſtant Bodies for Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour are <hi>dark,</hi> and for Figure <hi>round;</hi> it tells me alſo a great number of things in my Sleep; it preſents me (in Dreams) with abundance of Scenes; <hi>all which I disbelieve,</hi> for certain <hi>Difficulties,</hi> or <hi>an Inconceivable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in the things. In like manner, I know but few Men who believe <hi>Reaſon</hi> when it is not clear, but perplexed with <hi>Difficulties,</hi> or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Doubts, but eſpecially when there is a remarkable and manifeſt <hi>Inconceivableneſs.</hi> In that caſe we do not uſe to call it <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but, at
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57997:10"/>beſt, Probability and Opinion. Great <hi>Difficulties,</hi> and a too dark <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivableneſs,</hi> are ſuch a Ballance to whatſoever <hi>Reaſons;</hi> that they loſe the name of Reaſons, and are detruded into the rank of Likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods: and a very honourable rank it is, for ſuch kind of Reaſons.</p>
               <p>But he plainly ſhows what he would have, and what his deſperate Cauſe requires, when he ſo carefully adds: <hi>As to Contradictions, and Impoſſibilities, there will be many; whenever we will be reaſoning about ſuch things, as we underſtand not.</hi> I ſhall tell him; not, if there be <hi>many,</hi> as he ſays: but if there be <hi>any</hi> Contradictions, or Impoſſibilities; the thing propoſed becomes thereby, <hi>incredible.</hi> But if we will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, <hi>he ſays,</hi> about what we do not underſtand; there <hi>will be</hi> many Contradictions, and Impoſſibilities, in our Gueſſes concerning ſuch things. I anſwer, if thoſe Gueſſes do imply Contradictions, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities; they are ſuch Gueſſes, as none but Fools would make: for an Impoſſibility, or a Contradiction, is an obvious thing; of which, none but <hi>Philoſophers of Gotham</hi> will be guilty. If we are reaſoning about things, that we do not underſtand; and there is no occaſion, that I know of, to reaſon about any thing elſe: Why muſt we needs be overſeen as far as <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Impoſſibilities?</hi> are there no Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to be made, but thoſe groſs ones, Impoſſibilities and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions?</p>
               <p>It has been ever held, by the ſobereſt Divines, that <hi>Contradictions</hi> cannot be verified by the Divine Omnipotence, or Omniſcience, it ſelf: and that, when we ſay, <hi>all things are poſſible to God;</hi> we ought to mean it, of <hi>poſſible things;</hi> for as for <hi>Impoſſibilities,</hi> they are not the Objects of Omnipotence: God can no more do impoſſible things, than he can know falſe things to be true things, which (moſt certainly) is not knowable. A Sermon therefore, on behalf of Contradictions and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, cannot be more abſurd, than 'tis Heterodox, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally condemned, by Divines of all Perſwaſions. But this Dean has outfaced a Decree, of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in a matter, in which, if they had miſtaken, all the Univerſities of Chriſtendom had been obliged, to declare againſt them, and would have declared: therefore we need not to wonder, that now in a Sermon he as little ſcruples to contravene the known and agreed Senſe and Judgment, of all the ſeveral Denominations, or Sects, of Chriſtians. I ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57997:11"/>confeſs, I am for an ingenuous Liberty; and that too, in Queſtions of the greateſt Importance: but every body knows, how bitterly Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has always oppoſed (and ſtill oppoſes) all Diſſenters, either from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church: therefore, tho I ſhould not object it to another; yet to him, 'tis but his due, to tell him of the unparallel'd Immodeſty of his Diſſent, and Separation from the Catholick Church. That he has advanced a Hereſy, concerning the Bleſſed Trinity; condemned by General Councils, Decrees of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and Conſent of Writers: and he maintains it by Pleas, <hi>against</hi> Philoſophy and Reaſon, and <hi>for</hi> Contradictions and Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; no leſs generally reprobated on all hands, than his Hereſy it ſelf is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On his Anſwer to the firſt Objection.</head>
               <p>AFter ſuch a Defence of his Heterodoxies, as <hi>never was before heard;</hi> he proceeds to anſwer to <hi>two</hi> Objections, that <hi>never were made;</hi> or however, by none but himſelf. And tho it is a very injudicious, and needleſs Confeſſion, of a conſcience to a Man's own Inſufficience; to paſs over known, and very dangerous Objections: and anſwer on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Chimeras, and Follies, never ſuggeſted, or thought of, by any. Yet Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> is overſeen, much farther, and worſe, than that; for he not only overlooks the Objections of the Socinians, and replies to ſome Weakneſſes, that no body would have thought of, but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer: but his Anſwers are not, to thoſe Objections; but to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. The Reader ſhall not again rely upon me, if I do not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy him; and without the trouble of an intent Application; that this <hi>Maintainer of Paradoxes,</hi> had forgot his Objection, when he came to his Anſwer. He objects, firſt:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline"> It ſeems very unnatural, that God having made us reaſonable Creatures; and thereby made Reaſon to be to us, the Meaſure of Truth, and Falſhood: we ſhould be required, <hi>to believe without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> And if we muſt believe, with our Underſtandings; how can we believe what we do not underſtand?</q> I do not believe, as I ſaid; any Sect of Religious, ever made this or the like Objection. For 'tis very obvious to be ſeen, and underſtood; that tho we are made <hi>reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> Creatures, and do believe (or aſſent) with out Underſtandings:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57997:11"/>yet becauſe we cannot but be aware, that <hi>our</hi> Reaſons and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are finite and imperfect, often ſhort-ſighted, and as often over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing things; and the Wiſdom and Power of God, ſeen in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance and Structure of the World, moſt perfect; therefore, <hi>he</hi> may reveal many things to us, to be believed by us, tho <hi>we</hi> underſtand them not, nor have any other Cauſe of our believing them, but only God's Revelation of them. We ought to believe God, as Children do their Parents; or as we our ſelves believe ſage and ſober Perſons, in Matters belonging to their particular Art or Craft; that is to ſay, believe them <hi>on their Word;</hi> and for the juſt Opinion we have, of their ſuperiour Knowledg in ſuch Matters. To diſpute againſt this, is ſuch a degree of Folly; that, tho I dare not anſwer for every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Man: yet I know well, and any reaſonable body will ſuppoſe; there never was any Party of Men, or Sect of Religious, that could be ſo overſeen. I grant indeed, as 'tis in the Objection; that, <hi>Reaſon is the meaſure of Truth and Falſhood:</hi> but not the frail, fallible Reaſon, of Men; but <hi>the infallible</hi> Wiſdom of God. And in this, all Sects agree. The Objection therefore is Chimerical, and was never made by any ſort of Oppoſers: 'tis only a looſe Thought of this Preacher; and advanced, to help ſill up a crude Sermon. Well, but what is the wiſe Anſwer, to a ſilly Objection? Why, this.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline"> When an Objection is made againſt any thing, that it is (as we apprehend) <hi>without</hi> Reaſon, or againſt and <hi>contrary</hi> to Reaſon: the Objection is of no value, if ſuch thing is not the proper Object of Reaſon. Such as the <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Eſſences</hi> of things, their <hi>eſſential Reaſons, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions, Operations,</hi> and <hi>Properties:</hi> which no Man can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, are the Objects of Reaſon; or that any Man living can know any thing of them. And this, <hi>he adds farther,</hi> is all the Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibility, or Contradiction; that any can charge on the Trinity, or Incarnation.</q> By <hi>the Trinity,</hi> meaning his <hi>Trinity of Spirits.</hi> As I ſaid, in the name of Goodneſs, what is this Anſwer, to that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection? The Objection is; why ſhould reaſonable Creatures be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to believe things, without Reaſon? The Anſwer is; an Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of no value, if the Matter under diſpute is not the Object of Reaſon. Plainly, <hi>this</hi> Anſwer is not to <hi>that</hi> Objection; but concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite another thing: namely, that we muſt argue by Reaſon, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for or againſt ſuch things as are the Objects of Reaſon. But that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57997:12"/>this wild Anſwer might look life ſomewhat, he adds; the <hi>Subſtances, Eſſences, Reaſons, Properties, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions, and Operations of things,</hi> are not Objects of Reaſon: and no Man living can know any thing of them. Then, there is nothing, that is the Object of Reaſon; and no Man living knows any thing at all: for this Enumeration (Subſtances, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, Reaſons, Unions, Properties, Operations) comprehends all things; even the whole of created and uncreated Nature. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and confeſs'd by all Men, but this Gentleman; who ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in nothing ſo much as Paradoxes, and thinks the Pulpit and Preſs the likelieſt Places, to make 'em famous and remarkable: that, our Reaſon can be no otherwiſe imployed, but either about Subſtances, or their Unions, eſſential Reaſons, Operations, or Properties. What is it, Sir, I pray; but either, it is <hi>a Subſtance,</hi> or <hi>the Property,</hi> or <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of a Subſtance? For as to <hi>eſſential Reaſons,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions;</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (as well as Modes and Accidents) come under the general name of <hi>Properties.</hi> Riſibility (for inſtance)is an eſſential Reaſon, of <hi>Man as he is Man;</hi> and yet it is reckoned among <hi>the Properties:</hi> as well as Gracility, Groſſneſs, Agility, Slowneſs, Whiteneſs, Redneſs, and ſuch like Modes and Accidents, are called <hi>the Properties of particular Men;</hi> Properties by which they are diſtinguiſhed from one another. As eſſential Reaſons are <hi>but Properties;</hi> ſo Unions are but <hi>the Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> of Subſtances or their Properties. In ſhort, I ſay, that without being needleſly nice, <hi>Subſtances,</hi> with their <hi>Properties</hi> and <hi>Operations,</hi> will denote the whole Complex of things: their <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> are ſuperfluouſly added. And if theſe are not the Objects of Reaſon, Reaſon has no Objects at all: In truth, they are the only things about which Reaſon is converſant. Metaphyſicians conſider <hi>ſpiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> their <hi>Properties,</hi> and <hi>Operations:</hi> Natural Philoſophers conſider Bodies or <hi>corporeal Subſtances,</hi> their <hi>Operations</hi> and their <hi>Properties:</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Arts and Crafts are converſant about particular Bodies; as Phyſicians and Chirurgions about the humane Body; Chymiſts about Plants and Metals; the Lapidary about Jewels; the Apothecary about Drugs. Do theſe Artiſts know nothing about the <hi>Subſtances,</hi> their <hi>Properties</hi> or <hi>Operations,</hi> their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> and <hi>eſſential Reaſons;</hi> about which, both their Minds and Bodies are every day imployed? Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, when the Court deſired Mr. Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s to print this Sermon; they could not have done him a greater Diſſervice; than thus to prompt his Vanity, to expoſe his ſcandalous Inadverſions, to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57997:12"/>the View (and Scorn) of every body. It is well ſeen, why this Dean has preach'd againſt Philoſophy; Becauſe he hath very little himſelf. He has heard of Eſſence, Properties, Operations, eſſential Reaſons: and not knowing well what they mean, he gueſſes, they are things, that a zealous Preacher ought to beſtir himſelf againſt. A little more Zeal and Ignorance might have qualified him, to be one of my Lords the Inquiſitors; in the Inquiſition-Office at <hi>Lisbon:</hi> where lately they condemned an Engliſh <hi>Mare,</hi> to be burnt as <hi>a Witch;</hi> becauſe ſhe could ſignify the Hour of the Day, on a Watch or Clock, could dance to a Fiddle; with ſeveral ſuch little Feats, as are eaſily taught to Beaſts. Some Perſons interceded with the Holy Fathers, for <hi>the Mare;</hi> telling 'em, ſhe had been ſhown all over Chriſtendom: and that theſe Tricks had been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten taught, to other docile Beaſts, eſpecially to <hi>Elephants.</hi> But the Fathers, as zealous as ſome body elſe againſt what they did not underſtand, anſwered; ſhe ſhall be burnt: for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhe is not <hi>a Witch;</hi> be ſure, coming from <hi>England</hi> ſhe is <hi>a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſays, Laſtly: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>This</hi> (that the Queſtion is about <hi>Eſſences, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions, Properties</hi>) is all the <hi>Incomprehenſibleneſs,</hi> that can be charged on the Doctrines of the Trinity, and Incarnation.</q> For my part, to deal frankly; after all the buſtle and noiſe that has been made, on both ſides, about <hi>Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſibles:</hi> I know no Incomprehenſibleneſs, or Myſtery, in the Catholick Doctrines of the Trinity, and the Incarnation. I mean, as they are explained and declared by the Church; and now received, by the Unitarians themſelves: not, as they are perverted, and miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, by a (little) Faction; that have learned, from Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> to call themſelves <hi>Realiſts;</hi> as if their <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> were the only <hi>real Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Church</hi> teaches, that there is but one Eternal All-perfect Spirit; but one infinite ſpiritual Subſtance: and this is what we indifferently call <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Divinity,</hi> the <hi>Deity,</hi> the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the <hi>Divine Eſſence</hi> or Subſtance. As to the diſtinction of <hi>Perſons</hi> in the Deity; to uſe the Words of the Biſhop of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter:</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">When we conſider a Divine Eſſence, there can be no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57997:13"/> diſtinction conceived in it, but by <hi>different Modes</hi> of Subſiſtence; or (what is the ſame) different <hi>relative Properties.</hi>
                  </q> The Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then is the Divine Eſſence, Godhead, or Deity, conſider'd under three <hi>different Modes</hi> of Subſiſtence; which are called <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Properties,</hi> becauſe they <hi>diſtinguiſh,</hi> and becauſe a threefold <hi>Relation</hi> ariſes (in the Deity) from them: and <hi>Perſons</hi> they are called, becauſe diſtinguiſhing characterizing Properties; whether in a <hi>common</hi> Nature, or in <hi>particular</hi> Natures or Subſtances; when conſidered with the Nature or Subſtance, make what antient and conſtant Cuſtom nameth <hi>Perſons.</hi> Theſe Modes or Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are by ſome more particularly deſcribed; St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and (from him) the Divines of the Schools, inſiſt upon <hi>Intellectus, Notitia, &amp; Amor:</hi> or Original <hi>Mind</hi> or Wiſdom; the <hi>Logos</hi> or <hi>reflex Wiſdom,</hi> generated by Mind; and the Spiration of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love.</hi> The firſt, as generating, is named the <hi>Father;</hi> the ſecond, being generated, by a condeſcenſion to humane Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is called <hi>the Son:</hi> the third, being a Spiration, has the name of <hi>Spirit.</hi> I know not, as I ſaid, what Myſtery or Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibleneſs there is, in this account, which has been the Language and Explication of the Church ever ſince St. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> and not of the Latin Church only, but of the Greek; as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to prove at large, whenever leiſure and a fit opportunity ſhall ſerve.</p>
               <p>I ſee plainly, that the occaſion of calling the Trinity a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; except only among the Unlearned, or not Learned in Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtick and Philoſophical Terms, and the various Acceptations of them. I ſay, the occaſion of calling the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, a Myſtery, was this; becauſe the term <hi>Perſons;</hi> and again, <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> are uſed concerning the Deity, in a very different Senſe, from their Import or Meaning, when uſed of Men, or other created Beings. For all humane <hi>Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>Son,</hi> among Men, are diſtinguiſhed not only by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Modes</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> but by diſtinct Subſtances, Intellects, and Wills: but the Deity is but one Eſſence or ſpiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, with one Underſtanding, Will, and Energy in number. Thus the Idea of <hi>Perſons,</hi> and of <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> in God, implying a Notion ſo very different, from the meaning of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57997:13"/>ſame terms, when ſpoken of Men and created Beings: 'twas thought ſit, to ſay, they are uſed concerning God, in <hi>a myſtical</hi> Senſe; concerning other Beings, in a profane or <hi>common</hi> Senſe. A Senſe of Words or Terms, not ſo uſually applied; or rather, contrary to the vulgar and ſecular Uſe of them, was named <hi>Myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery:</hi> at firſt, I judg, only by the leſs Learned; afterwards, to conciliate the greater Reverence to the Article, by the more Learned alſo.</p>
               <p>As to the Incarnation. The Doctrine of the Church, has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, in the leaſt unconceivable or myſterious: <hi>viz.</hi> That the Godhead, (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; or (as St. <hi>John</hi>) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>tabernacl'd</hi> and <hi>dwelleth</hi> in the Lord Chriſt. Not as in Prophets, <hi>occaſionally,</hi> and <hi>in meaſure:</hi> but as the Soul in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>viz. always</hi> enlightning and actuating him; and exerting by him and in him the Divine Attributes, Omnipotence and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; ſo that 'tis truly ſaid, <hi>God was made Man,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Chriſt is God.</hi> Yet not as <hi>Eutyches</hi> exceeded in the caſe; ſo that God was <hi>changed</hi> into Man, and the Humanity was <hi>Deified;</hi> which, beſides that 'tis blaſphemous, is alſo contradictory: but ſo, that <hi>the Terms</hi> uſed are to be interpreted by the Doctrine; not the Doctrine by the Terms: That is to ſay; We believe, that God is eſſentially <hi>Omni-preſent:</hi> but dwelling in the Lord Chriſt, as the Soul in the Body; that is, <hi>always inlightning and actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, by an eternal indiſſoluble <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion; exerting alſo in him and by him the proper Characters of the Divinity,</hi> Omniſcience (the Knowledg of <hi>the future,</hi> and of <hi>the Thoughts,</hi> &amp;c.) and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that is the Power <hi>of Miracles,</hi> and <hi>of Creation,</hi> as was ſeen in the caſe of the multiplied Loaves and Fiſhes; therefore we rightly affirm <hi>a Communication of Idioms,</hi> as to the terms: Namely, that <hi>in reſpect of ſuch an Incarnation,</hi> God became Man; and the Lord Chriſt was true God.</p>
               <p>I ſay, there is nothing in theſe two Explications, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, or myſterious: there was no reaſon, that <hi>F. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus,</hi> or (that very learned Perſon) <hi>J. Crellius,</hi> ſhould cry <hi>Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and <hi>Myſtery;</hi> and as little that Catholick Writers ſhould defend theſe Doctrines, under the name of great Difficulties,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57997:14"/>myſterious and inconceivable Articles. There is nothing in them, that can puzzle either a learned or a diſcerning Man; nothing that ſhocks our Reaſon, or to which any Syſtem of Philoſophy yet known makes any oppoſition. If what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the Terms of theſe Articles, is made intelligible, nay obvious; and if the Explication implies nothing, contrary to Philoſophy or Reaſon, that is, to <hi>experimental</hi> or to <hi>natural</hi> Knowledg: I ſhall be glad to be taught, why theſe Articles muſt be called <hi>Myſteries;</hi> a name that offends ſo many, and in which others ſo much delight, both (in my poor Judgment) without Cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To his Anſwer unto the laſt Objection.</head>
               <p>THE Second Objection is this: <q rend="inline">To what purpoſe can ſuch a Revelation ſerve, or of what uſe can ſuch a Faith be; which is concerning things that we cannot underſtand, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend?</q> I do not think, any Sect of Religious ever made this Objection: for how could it eſcape them, that, <hi>on the one ſide,</hi> the Articles of Religion are <hi>not altogether inconceivable,</hi> or unintelligible; and that <hi>on the other hand,</hi> there is ſcarce any thing in Nature, or in Art, that is <hi>altogether conceivable</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible?</p>
               <p>But let us hear what the Preacher ſays upon it. He ſays: 1. <q rend="inline">We may uſe the World, <hi>as fully;</hi> and every thing in it, <hi>to as good purpoſe;</hi> as if <hi>we underſtood</hi> the Reaſons, and internal Natures of things.</q> No, Triſler; not ſo fully, nor to ſo good purpoſe, as if we <hi>better</hi> underſtood the Natures of things. Nay, we can make no uſe at all of it; but only ſo far forth, as we underſtand the Nature, and Reaſons of things in it. We can uſe nothing, to any purpoſe, till we know or underſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of its Nature: and no farther can we apply it, and uſe it, than we underſtand its Nature, and know its Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers. The matter is ſo plain, I will dwell no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon it.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57997:14"/>
               <p>He ſays, Laſtly: <q rend="inline">The <hi>lapſed</hi> State of Nature, makes <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Knowledg</hi> neceſſary: when Man had ſinned, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited the Favour of God, and his natural Immortality; and <hi>the Light of Nature</hi> could not teach him, how to make Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Sin; or give any hope that God would beſtow Immortal Life.</q> True, but not in the leaſt to the purpoſe: 'tis no Anſwer, to <hi>that</hi> Objection; but to another: namely, to this; why Revelation, or a <hi>ſupernatural Knowledg,</hi> is neceſſary; or however, highly requiſite? The Objection was, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Revelation, and Faith, <hi>not intelligible,</hi> or <hi>not conceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> The Anſwer is, only concerning Revelation (or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Knowledg) in general, why it was given to Men? There is a great difference between <hi>ſupernaturally revealed,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable:</hi> the whole Chriſtian Religion, the Precepts as well as Faith of it, is <hi>a ſupernatural Revelation;</hi> and yet a Syſtem ſo intelligible, that it muſt be taught to the Women, to the Poor, and even to little Children. It was not made the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>ſupernatural Revelation;</hi> for its Difficulty, Myſteriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Tranſcendency of the humane Underſtanding: but <hi>to aſcertain the Truth of it;</hi> and to <hi>enforce its Authority,</hi> in the World.</p>
               <p>I have done with the Sermon; and ſhall hope that ſuch <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſts</hi> for the Articles of the Catholick Church, as firſt corrupt thoſe Articles by an Heretical Senſe put on them; and then betray them, by a Defence partly falſe, and partly weak; will no more be incouraged to print, as well as preach, their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Follies. I know, 'tis an uſual Civility of the Court, eſpecially to ſuch Divines as are Dignified, Doctors and Deans; to deſire them, to print their Sermons: I know too, that ſome heard this Sermon, and moved the printing of it; who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood well the Heretical Aim of the Preacher, and expected it would be anſwered by ſome or other that underſtood the Doctrine of the Church, and how to defend it. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it were better, that treacherous Defences, and falſe Repreſentations, of the Articles of our Faith, might not be countenanced out of a (dangerous) Civility to the erroneous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57997:15"/>Perſon: or Poiſon be ſold, and even cried about the Streets; from an expectation of ſome good Antidote, that may be found againſt it; I mean, that it might not be ſold and cried about, by direction of an Honourable Court, only in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment to the mere Station or Poſt, in which Mr. Preacher hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to be.</p>
               <p>As for him, we know before-hand, what his Defence will be; the ſame that he always makes, on this occaſion: as he has an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd to the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads, to Dr. <hi>S</hi>—<hi>th,</hi> and to the Author of <hi>A Judgment of the Controverſy, between Dr.</hi> S—th <hi>and Dr.</hi> Sher-Iock; that his Oppoſer is a Sabellian, or a Socinian. By which Inſolencies, and Falſhoods, he has at laſt ſo provok'd every body; that the Charge of Socinianiſm is now brought home, to himſelf: and may it be left, where 'tis ſo well deſerved; and ſo truly imputed. There is nothing more true, than that his Sentiments about the Trinity are the ſame, with thoſe of <hi>Laelius Socinus, V. Gentilis, G. Blandrata, J. Liſmaninus,</hi> and other Founders of Socinianiſm: and that he can never defend the Unity of God, on thoſe Principles. He will be led, by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Chain of Conſequences, to the Scheme of <hi>Fauſtus Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> which is built on this Miſtake, common to him and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> that <hi>Perſon</hi> and a particular <hi>intelligent Eſſence</hi> or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, are equivalent terms, ſo that in ſaying <hi>three Perſons,</hi> you ſay alſo <hi>three Eſſences.</hi> The Ground of <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> and which if true, all Men grant that his Scheme alſo of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be true, is, that <hi>Perſon</hi> and a particular <hi>intelligent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> are the ſame; that as often as you multiply one, you multiply the other: from whence <hi>Fauſtus</hi> concluded, we muſt not ſay three Divine <hi>Perſons;</hi> becauſe 'tis a granting three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Subſtances</hi> or Eſſences, which would be three <hi>Gods.</hi> Leſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſhould deny, that he takes the ſame Ground with <hi>Fauſtus Socinus;</hi> and therefore, that <hi>in conſequence</hi> their Schemes are coincident; I will ſubjoin his very Words: <q rend="inline">A <hi>Perſon,</hi> and an <hi>intelligent Subſtance,</hi> are reciprocal terms: and three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Perſons,</hi> are three diſtinct numerical <hi>Subſtances;</hi> and one numerical <hi>intelligent Subſtance,</hi> is but one numerical <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                  </q> Vindic. p. 69. Again, <q rend="inline">How can <hi>three</hi> diſtinct Perſons have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57997:15"/> but <hi>one</hi> numerical Subſtance? What is the Diſtinction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Eſſence, Perſonality,</hi> and <hi>Subſiſtence?</hi>
                  </q> p. 139.</p>
               <p>To conclude; All the Difference between <hi>F. Socinus</hi> and this Man is; <hi>Socinus</hi> ſaw the Conſequences of his Principles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Monitor: the other, even when admoniſh'd, does not, or (as ſome think) will not ſee them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT By another Hand.</head>
            <p>THIS Author has told his Reader, <hi>p.</hi> 7. that Dr. <hi>Sh.</hi> hath not indeed in this Sermon declar'd expreſly, what kind of Trinity he pleads for; but he intimates it, and plainly points to it, at <hi>p.</hi> 7, <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. But beſides what is there ſaid, for making known the Dean's Doctrine of <hi>a Trinity of Spirits and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> I conceive it may give greater Evidence of it, to cite a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage or two concerning it out of his Book, <hi>The Vindication of the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. where we find, <hi>p.</hi> 66. <q rend="inline">It is plain, the Perſons are perfectly diſtinct, for they are three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and infinite Minds.—To ſay, they are three Divine Perſons, and not three diſtinct Infinite Minds, is both Hereſy and Non-ſenſe. They are three intelligent Beings. Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are as really diſtinct Perſons as <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> (p. 105.) They are three Holy Spirits, <hi>p.</hi> 258. There is no Contradiction that three Infinite Minds ſhould be abſolutely perfect, in Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Juſtice and Power; for theſe are Perfections that may be in more than one, <hi>p.</hi> 81. And <hi>p.</hi> 47. We muſt allow the Divine Perſons to be real ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Beings—the three Divine Perſons are ſubſtantially di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. </q> This now is that Doctrine which Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> muſt be underſtood to plead for in this Sermon. It is the Myſtery of this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57997:16"/>Trinity, of which he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>The Inconceivableneſs can be no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Truth of the Revelation, or that Senſe of the Words which contains ſuch Myſteries.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>things</hi> (he ſays) <hi>we muſt believe, tho we do not ſee; things which we have no natural Notion or Conception of, things that are not evident to natural Reaſon.</hi> The meaning is plainly this; We muſt believe his Doctrine of three diſtinct and Infinite Minds and Spirits, however it does in our cleareſt Reaſon, improv'd alſo by moſt evident Revelation, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Worſhip of three Gods; for what is ſo evident both in Reaſon and Revelation, as that God is <hi>one Infinite Mind and Spirit,</hi> and not three? But Dr. <hi>Sh.</hi> has devis'd ſome pretty new terms, ſuch as <hi>Self-conſciouſneſs</hi> and <hi>mutual Conſciouſneſs,</hi> whereby to elude the Teſtimony of Holy Scripture concerning the perfect Oneneſs of God: but Reaſon contradicts him, and will not ſuffer him to deſtroy that glorious Attribute under the notion of <hi>unconceivable Myſtery:</hi> She ſays, it's not Myſtery, but a plain Inconſiſtency; therefore Dr. <hi>Sh.</hi> would have her Mouth ſtopp'd, or our Ears ſtopp'd, that we may not hear what Reaſon ſays, tho in conſent with Revelation; or at leaſt that we ſhould give no heed to what ſhe ſays.</p>
            <p>Our Author has told us, that the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Decree condemns this Doctrine as <hi>Impious and Heretical;</hi> contrary to the Doctrine of the Catholick Church, and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But if we will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Preacher, the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads have paſs'd that Sentence, becauſe they give too much heed to natural Reaſon and Philoſophy; and exalt what thoſe ſay, even above Revelation. This brings to my mind what the late Archbiſhop of Bleſſed Memory determin'd in the Diſpute between Reaſon and Revelation. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> did him a great deal of Right in a Sermon upon the ſad occaſion of his Death, I hope he will not now deſpiſe his Judgment. That great Man upon 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. ſays, 1. <hi>That Reaſon is the Faculty whereby Revelations are to be diſcerned.</hi> 2. <hi>All ſupernatural Revelation ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the Truth of the Principles of natural Religion.</hi> 3. <hi>All Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings about Divine Revelations muſt neceſſarily be governed by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of natural Religion,</hi> that is, <q rend="inline">by thoſe Apprehenſions which Men naturally have of the Divine Perfections, and by the clear Notions of Good and Evil, which are imprinted upon our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57997:16"/>Becauſe we have no other way to judg of what is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God, and credible to be reveal'd by him, and what not, but by natural Notions which we have of God, and of his eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Perfections—and by theſe Principles likewiſe we are to interpret what God hath revealed; and when any doubt ariſeth concerning the Meaning of any Divine Revelation, (as that of the Holy Scriptures) we are to govern our ſelves in the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of it, by what is moſt agreeable to thoſe natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which we have of God; and we have all the Reaſon in the World to reject that Senſe which is contrary thereto. 4. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be receiv'd as a Revelation from God, which plainly contradicts the Principles of natural Religion, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws the Certainty of them.</q> Under this Head that excellent Man concludes; <q rend="inline">That a Miracle is not enough to give credit to a Prophet that teacheth any thing, contrary to that natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Men have, <hi>That there is but one God, who only ought to be worſhipped.</hi>
               </q> Thus we ſee that in the Judgment of the late Archbiſhop, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Trinity would not be made credible, tho a Miracle ſhould be wrought in Teſtimony of it, becauſe it contradicts the Principles of natural Religion, that is, of natural Reaſon.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
